There's three major components
or subsystems to the HotSpot
Java Virtual Machine.
Those are the VM
runtime, an area that
provides a runtime
environment for things that
sit on top of the runtime
environment, a garbage
collector, or a memory
manager, a thing that
manages object allocation
and garbage collection,
and a JIT compiler, a component
that takes Java bytecode
and generates native
assembly instructions
for the underlying platform.
The VM runtime-- it has many
responsibilities, including
command line option parsing, the
starting and stopping of a JVM,
error handling, exception
handling, class loading,
and the Java
bytecode interpreter.
It also handles the Java native
interface, thread management,
and synchronization.
The command line
options that you specify
are handled by the runtime.
The good news is you
don't have to know
a lot of the internal details
about the HotSpot VM runtime.
From a performance
perspective, the understanding
of what it does and that is
the component that manipulates
the command line options,
exception handling, error
handling, class loading, is
done through the VM Runtime.
The garbage collector
or memory manager
is responsible for object
allocation and reclamation,
in other words,
garbage collection.
Most commonly this
component is thought
of as the garbage collector.
The behavior and efficiency
of a garbage collector
can heavily influenced the
performance and responsiveness
of a Java application.
As a result, choosing an
appropriate garbage collector
and tuning it are usually the
most frequently taken actions
to realize performance
improvements in a Java
application.
The HotSpot JVM has four
different garbage collectors.
All four garbage collectors are
known as generational garbage
collectors.
I'll explain what a
generational garbage
collector in just a moment.
Two of the garbage
collectors are
known as stop the world
type garbage collectors.
The other two are a combination
of a stop the world garbage
collector and a mostly
concurrent garbage collector.
A stop the world
garbage collector
is one that stops all
Java application threads
while the garbage collector
is doing its work.
A mostly concurrent
garbage collector
is one that concurrently
excuse most of the time
while the Java
application is running.
Back to the generational garbage
collectors, most allocated
objects are unreachable
or eligible to be
reclaimed very quickly.
And there exists
few objects that
live for a longer period of
time than younger objects.
As a result, a generational
garbage collector
is one that partitions the Java
heap into two or more regions
or generations.
The most common form of a
generational garbage collector
is one that has a
young generation
and an old generation.
The young generation is for
newly allocated objects.
And the old generation is
for longer lived objects.
The premise at work here is
that the longer an object lives,
the JVM's memory manager
or garbage collector
will eventually migrate an
object from young generation
to old generation the
longer that object lives.
In Java 6 and Java
7 HotSpot JVMs,
there's a third generation
called permanent generation,
which holds metadata such
as class data structures.
But objects themselves
are not migrated
to the permanent generation
from the old generation
to permanent generation.
Sometimes folks are
confused a little bit
by the additional
permanent generation.
The permanent
generation, again, is
used to hold metadata and
class data structures,
not Java object
waste, in the same way
that young generation and old
generation handle Java objects.
In Java 8 HotSpot JVMs,
permanent generation
is eliminated in
favor of a space
or a region referred
to as a metaspace.
It generally holds
the same data as what
was held in the
permanent generation.
But it is managed differently
in Java HotSpot JVMs.
A few more details on
the young generation
and old generation and
permanent generation,
along with how they fit
together are covered
a little later in this lesson.
For the choices of garbage
collectors in the HotSpot JVM,
there's a serial
garbage collector,
which is a single threaded
stop the world young generation
collector, and a single threaded
stop the world old generation
collector.
It was HotSpot's first
garbage collector.
It also tends to have
the smallest memory
footprint of the HotSpot
garbage collectors.
A second garbage collector
called the throughput garbage
collector, otherwise
commonly known
as the parallel collector,
is a multithreaded stop
the world young
generation collector
and either a single threaded or
a multithreaded stop the world
old generation collector.
In the most recent
Java HotSpot JVMs,
the default collector for
what is called a server class
machine is a multithreaded young
generation and old generation
collector.
A server class
machine is defined
as a machine that has 2
gigabyte or more of RAM
and has 2 or more
virtual processors.
The one exception to this rule
is that on 32-bit Windows,
the default collector is the
serial garbage collector.
A third garbage collector called
a concurrent garbage collector,
otherwise commonly known as
CMS, is a multithreaded stop
the world young generation
collector, a mostly concurrent
old generation collector.
There are phases to
the old generation
collector that run concurrently
with the application.
And there are some phases of
it that are stop the world.
A fourth garbage
collector called
G1 is a relatively
new garbage collector.
It was officially supported
as of Java HotSpot 7 Update 4.
G1 is a region
base multithreaded
stop the world young
generation collector
and a combination of
a mostly concurrent
and stop the world old
generation collector.
The major difference
between G1 and CMS
is that G1 compacts the old
generation without requiring
a full GC event.
The last component, the third
component, the JIT compiler,
its responsibility is to turn
Java bytecode into native code
for the underlying platform.
The goal of course is to offer
improved execution performance.
Huge application
performance improvements
are realized as the
result of JIT compilation.
There's a couple of JIT compiler
choices in a HotSpot JVM.
One is the Client
JVM, which is designed
for the rapid
application startup.
Another is the Server JVM,
which is highly optimized,
producing high performing
generated code.
It pays a penalty for
application startup,
but also realizes peak
application performance.
A recent addition called Tiered
is the best of both Client
and Server.
So at application startup,
it behaves like a Client JVM
and continues to
optimize until it
reaches the same level
of generated code
and optimizations as we would
see with the Server JVM.
So TieredCompilation is
the default for Java 8.